Updated January 8, 2021

Ning Zou

PhD student, UX researcher University of Pittsburgh, School of Computing and Information

③ ning-zou.qithub.io **☑** niz19@pitt.edu **□** 315.289.2369

I am interested in utilizing mixed-method approach to understand the human factors for emerging intelligent and social information technologies; and to advance people's capabilities of accessing and understanding to their personal health data/information.

Keywords: Human data/information interaction, Health informatics and Personal informatics.

SKILLS Research Methods: Contextual design, Ethnography, Field study, Interview,

Survey, Usability testing

Tools: Numpy, Pandas, Scipy, NLTK

Programming: Python, HTML/CSS, R, SQL

Software: MySQL, SPSS, Tableau, ATLAS.ti, NVivo, Adobe Creative Suite

EDUCATION University of Pittsburgh Pittsburgh, PA

Ph.D. in Library and Information Science 08/2017 - Present

Advisor: Dr. Daqing He

Syracuse University

Syracuse, NY

M.S. in Library and Information Science 08/2014 – 05/2016

Certificate Advanced Study in Data Science

Heilongjiang UniversityB.S. in Information Management

09/2007 - 07/2011

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Exploring Alzheimer's disease and related Dementia (ADRD) caregivers' information behavior in social media [1]

Advisors: Dr. Daqing He (PITT), Dr. Bo Xie (UT-Austin) 01/2020 – Present Research on examine ADRD caregivers' online information exchange on Reddit. The results provide insights to design an interactive system for engaging clinicians and automatic algorithms; and to better support clinician's interventions for ADRD patients.

- Data Processing: clean, parse and classify the online posts through Reddit public API.
- Content Analysis: developed coding scheme and utilized qualitative content analysis to identify the types of ADRD-related information exchange in social media;
- ♦ Data Analysis: conducting network analysis to discover caregivers' interaction patterns.

Investigating people's behavior in Internet of things for health (H-IoT) tracked personal health data^[2]

Advisors: Dr. Daqing He (PITT)

05/2019 - Present

Research on understanding people's lifestyle self-management needs that related to H-IoT generated personal health data.

- Survey: designed and conducted a web survey to gather data directly from prediabetic H-IoT users about the kinds of data they need to track to facilitate self-managing their health;
- Interview: utilizing a mixed-method approach that combines both interview studies with co-design studies to uncover people's preferences and constraints of interacting with the data generated by H-IoT.

Analyzing knowledge nodes and relationships for building a knowledge network of disease^[5]

Advisors: Dr. Jian Qin (Syracuse University)

01/2016 - 09/2016

Fall 17, Spring 18

Research assistant for the *GenBank Metadata* project. This project intends to investigate the knowledge organization systems' capabilities in responding to the rapidly changing biomedical and disease terms.

 Content Analysis: uncover and identify the types of knowledge nodes and relationships between these nodes from precision medicine literature.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Graduate-level course assistant (University of Pittsburgh)

LIS2030: Data and Information in Systems Spring 21, 20

LIS2021: Identifying Information Needs in Knowledge

LIS2975: Research Data Management

Organizations

LIS2771: Academic Libraries

LIS2023: Integrating Solutions for Knowledge Organizations

INFSCI2140: Information Storage and Retrieval

INFSCI2440: Artificial Intelligence

LIS2850: Information Professional's Role in Teaching

and Learning

Fall 20, Fall 19

Summer 20

Fall18, Spring 19

Summer 18

Summer 18

Graduate-level course design (University of Pittsburgh)

LIS2030: Data and Information in Systems Summer 19

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- [1] Wang, Z., **Zou, N.**, Xie, B., He, D., Luo, Z., Hilsabeck R. C., & Aguirre, A. (forthcoming). Characterizing dementia caregivers' information exchange on social media: exploring an expert-machine co-development. (iConference 2021)
- [2] **Zou**, **N.**, He, D., & Liang, S. (2020, October). "Your Personal Health Data Can Tell": Exploring Prediabetic Adult's Lifestyle Self-Management with H-loT Technology. (ASIS&T 2020)
- [3] He, D., Wang, Z., Thaker, K., & **Zou**, **N**. (2020, July). Translation and Expansion: Enabling Laypeople Access to the COVID-19 Academic Collection. *Data and Information Management*, 4(3), 117 190.
- [4] **Zou**, **N.**, He, D., & Liang, S.(2020, March). Issues and challenges of user and data interaction in health related IoT: A systematic review. *Library Hi Tech*, Vol. 38 No.4, pp. 769 782
- [5] Qin, J., **Zou**, **N.** (2017, March). Structures and Relations of Knowledge Nodes: Exploring a Knowledge Network of Disease from Precision Medicine Research Publications. (iConference 2017)

ACADEMIC SERVICES

Reviewer of Aslib Journal of Information Management (SSCI)

Reviewer of Journal of Librarianship & Information Science (SSCI)

Reviewer of ASIS&T Asia-Pacific Regional Conference (2020)

PhD student representative for Pitt SCI faculty search committee (2018 – 2019)

Student volunteer for IDCC (2018)

HONORS AND SCHOLARSHIP

Bertha G. Louik Scholarship (University of Pittsburgh)	2018
Blanche E. Woolls Scholarship(University of Pittsburgh)	2018
Clair Pyle Fund Scholarship (University of Pittsburgh)	2018